Guide to the Ransom Rathbone Patrick Papers, 1940-1960
Duke University. University Archives
Ransom Rathbone Patrick papers 1940s-1960s
Duke University. University Archives
Patrick, Ransom Rathbone, 1906-1971.
2.2 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
Ransom Patrick was a painter, sculptor and professor of Aesthetics and Art at Duke from the 1940s through the 1960s. His collection includes course materials, photographs of artworks, essays, correspondence and news clippings. Materials range in date from the 1940s-1960s.
uapatrickrr
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Ransom Rathbone Patrick Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974, 1977, 1984.
Biographical Note
Ransom Rathbone Patrick was born in 1906 in Santa Barbara, CA. He began as a graphic artist, apprenticing as a sign-painter and newspaper artist and eventually became a freelance artist in Seattle, San Francisco, Cleveland and New York. In 1944, he received is B.A. from the University of Washington, in 1947 and 1959, respectively, he received his M.F.A. and Ph.D. from Princeton University. He taught at Oberlin College, the University of British Columbia, the University of Minnesota and Western Reserve University before joining the Duke faculty as chair of the Aesthetics, Art and Music Department at Duke University in 1954. Specializing in American and modern art, Patrick also designed the ceremonial flag of Duke University. He died in April of 1971.
Collection Overview
Collection contains course materials, Patrick's academic essays and lectures, academic and personal correspondence, Duke administrative and departmental memoranda and documents, photographs of Patrick's murals and sculptures, and news clippings relating to Duke University events.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Art, American.; Art, Modern.; Duke University. Dept. of Aesthetics, Art and Music.; Duke University. Flags.; Patrick, Ransom Rathbone, 1906-1971.
Related Material
Art and Art History (Dept. of) Records, 1942-1985.
University Archives. Duke University.
Trinity College of Arts and Sciences, Office of the Dean records, 1934-2003.
University Archives. Duke University.
Edens (A. Hollis) Records, 1949-1960
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Photograph, undated (Box 1)
  - Patrick Paper, "Evaluation of Picasso"
  - Patrick Paper, "Evaluation of Picasso"
  - San Fernando College Correspondence, 1964
  - Hydrodynamics Flow Diagram, 1964
  - Deryl Hart Correspondence, 1962
  - Speeches, 1957 and undated
  - News Clippings, Football Photo, Miscellaneous, 1954-62
  - Zoology Lecture Notes, 1943
  - Oriental Art Lecture Notes, undated
  - Scientific Though Lecture Notes, undated
  - Paper, "What is a Man Worth," 1946
  - Gary Tabor Alumni Letter, Class of '59
  - Correspondence, 1942-48
  - Paper, "Failure of Modern Sculpture," Copy of First Draft
  - Metaphysics - Copy of First Quarter Outline
  - Philosophy Lecture Notes
  - Formal Sciences Lecture Notes
  - Studio Program Change Proposal, undated
  - Jack's [Major Jack C. Thompson] Correspondence from Vietnam, 1968
  - Photographs, unlabeled (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Clippings and Speeches, 1957-62
  - Academic Papers, undated
  - University Research Council Documents, 1956-57
  - Personal Correspondence, 1954-61
  - Research Materials
  - Art 301 Materials
  - Record Library Report, May 1957
  - Art Criticism 121
  - Ad Club Talk
  - American Society for Aesthetics, 1957
  - Department Correspondence, 1961-64
  - Department Reports and Requests
  - To Be Answered, 1961-62
  - Art History Course Notes
  - Aesthetics Course
  - Personal Letters
  - Interview with Jack Eipper, 1961
  - Long-Range Planning Committee Report, undated (Oversize 3)
  - Correspondence and Photos Regarding Murals, 1958
  - Sample Questions from Past Quizzes, undated
  - Correspondence, Course Materials, Miscellaneous, 1947-70